Guide to the Alsop Family Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- Additional Material, Accession 1987-M-071
  - Family Papers, 1760-1986; Series I
    Their youngest son, John Alsop, an insurance executive in Hartford, was the Republican candidate in the 1962 Connecticut gubernatorial race. He lost the election to John Dempsey.
    At the beginning of the series, the General portion includes a substantial collection of recipe books and cards belonging to several Alsop women. Materials thereafter are arranged alphabetically by individual. Corinne Alsop's personal correspondence, primarily letters received from her husband Joseph W. Alsop (1876-1953), comprise the bulk of her papers. Mrs. Alsop's correspondence additionally includes letters from her friend, actress Ruth Draper, and updates on her children from the nanny, Agnes Guthrie. All correspondence-related folders contain both incoming and outgoing letters and are arranged chronologically.
    The papers of Joseph W. Alsop (1876-1953) consist of fairly routine personal papers and Connecticut State Senate reports from 1909 pertaining to his service on the Roads and Bridges Committee. Photographs, printed material, correspondence, political cartoons, clippings, and ephemera document the gubernatorial run of John Alsop in 1962. The majority of these materials are photographs, the bulk of which are campaign shots taken by professional photographers. They include posed photographs of the Alsop family and candid shots of John Alsop meeting and greeting his constituents at fundraisers and other functions. The series also includes World War I paraphernalia of Joseph W. Alsop's (1876-1953) brother, John deKoven Alsop (1879-1926).
    - General
      - Artifacts, 1760, 1880s (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - Baby clothes, 1849
        General note
        See: box 19, folder 17
      - Clippings, 1927-1968 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - Correspondence, 1830-1910 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - Deeds, 1700s, 1870-1890s, undated (Box 1, Folder 4-6)
        See also: box 20, folder 18 - 19
      - Financial, 1880-1883 (Box 1, Folder 7-8)
      - Genealogy, undated (Box 1, Folder 9-12)
      - History, undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
      - Newspapers [ The American Mercury ], 1790s
        See: Series IV, Deeds and Miscellania, Box 4 of the original accession.
      - Printed material [re: Avon, CT], undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
      - Legal, 1850-1889 (Box 2, Folder 15-16)
      - Recipes, 1809, undated (Box 2, Folder 17-23)
      - Recipes, 1843-1869, 1907, undated (Box 3, Folder 24-29)
    - Alsop, Corinne (1886-1971)
      See also: box 14, folder 1-3; box 15, folder 4-6
      - Correspondence
        - General, 1923-1970, n.d (Box 4, Folder 30-32)
        - Alsop, Joseph, 1912-1920, undated (Box 4, Folder 33-39)
        - Draper, Ruth, 1933-1946, undated (Box 5, Folder 40)
        - Guthrie, Agnes, undated (Box 5, Folder 41)
        - Longworth, Alice Roosevelt, 1929, undated (Box 5, Folder 42)
      - Genealogy, 1932, undated (Box 5, Folder 43)
      - Interview, undated (Box 5, Folder 44)
      - Plays, 1913-1918 (Box 5, Folder 45)
      - Scrapbooks, 1902, 1904
    - Alsop, John (1915-2000)
      - Childhood, 1924-1925 (Box 5, Folder 46)
      - Correspondence, 1952-1983, undated (Box 5, Folder 47)
      - Gubernatorial race
        - Ephemera, 1962 (Box 5, Folder 48)
        - Printed material, 1962 (Box 5, Folder 49)
        - Photographs, 1962 (Box 5, Folder 50-51)
          See also: box 18, folder 13
        - Photographs, 1962 (Box 6, Folder 52-58)
        - Political cartoons, 1962
          See: box 18, folder 14
        - Scrapbooks
          - 1958 (Box 7, Folder 59)
          - 1958 (Box 8, Folder 60)
          - 1962 (Box 9, Folder 61)
      - Miscellaneous, 1962
        See: box 18, folder 15
    - Alsop, John deKoven (1879-1926) [military], 1919 (Box 10, Folder 62)
    - Alsop, Joseph W. (1876-1953)
      - Biographical, 1941, 1953, undated (Box 10, Folder 63)
      - Correspondence [mainly requests for information on his father], 1935-1944 (Box 10, Folder 64)
      - Honors, 1953
        See: box 16, folder 7
      - Scrapbook, undated
        See: box 17, folder 12
      - Senate reports, 1909-1911 (Box 10, Folder 65-71)
      - Senate reports, 1909-1911 (Box 11, Folder 72)
      - Twentieth-fifth wedding anniversary, 1934 (Box 11, Folder 73)
    - Alsop, Richard, "An Early 19th Century Yankee Entrepreneur", 1986
    - Alsop, Stewart
      - Correspondence [re: power of attorney for Uncle Monroe Robinson], 1939 (Box 11, Folder 75)
      - Writings [clippings], 1957, 1959
        See: box 18, folder 16
    - Beach, Helen (cousin of Joseph W. Alsop (1876-1953), "Reminiscences", 1909 (Box 11, Folder 76-78)
    - Cole, Francis (second husband of Corinne Alsop), 1966 (Box 11, Folder 79)
    - Oliver, George (family relation), 1847-1953 (Box 11, Folder 80)
  - Photographs, 1886-1887, undated; Series II
    The photographs are arranged by individual. Many are unlabeled and unidentified and are assumed to depict members of the Alsop family over three generations. Oversized photographs are located in their appropriately sized boxes and are cross-referenced. The photographs encompass a variety of subjects, from portraiture of members of the Alsop family and childhood photographs of Corinne Robinson Alsop, to group photographs of Joseph W. Alsop's (1876-1953) class at Yale University. Several photographs of the Alsop's farm, Wood Ford, are also included. Photographs relating to John Alsop's 1962 gubernatorial campaign are in Series I.
    - Alsop, Aimée, undated (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Alsop, Corinne, undated
    - Alsop, Frank, undated (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - Alsop, John (1915-2000), 1962
      See also: box 4, folder 50-58.
    - Alsop, John deKoven (1879-1926), undated (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - Alsop, Joseph W. (1838-1891, undated (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - Alsop, Joseph W. (1876-1953), 1898, 1938, undated (Box 12, Folder 5-7)
      See also: box 16, folder 8-11.
    - Alsop, Stewart [school group photograph], undated (Box 12, Folder 8)
    - Beach, Helen, undated (Box 12, Folder 9)
    - Draper, Ruth, undated (Box 12, Folder 10)
    - Wood Ford Farm, undated (Box 12, Folder 11)
    - Unidentified, undated (Box 12, Folder 12-13)
  - Roosevelt Family, 1861-1933; Series III; 1.5 linear feet (4 boxes)
    This small collection of correspondence between members of the Roosevelt family is arranged alphabetically and includes letters from Theodore Roosevelt, Sr. to his wife, Mittie, as well as the correspondence of Corinne Alsop's mother, Corinne Roosevelt Robinson. Also included are personal letters written by her sister, Anna "Bamie" Roosevelt Cowles, and childhood friend and wife of President Theodore Roosevelt, Edith Kermit Carow Roosevelt. Many of these letters deal with their respective family and social lives; the handwriting is difficult to read.
    - Robinson, Corinne Roosevelt, 1902-1933 (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - Roosevelt, Anna "Bamie", 1869-1870, undated (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - Roosevelt, Edith Kermit Carow, undated (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - Roosevelt, Theodore, Sr., 1861-1877 (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - Roosevelts, [unsigned], undated (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Oversize, Series IV
    - Alsop, Corinne (1886-1971)
      - Photographs, undated (Box 14, Folder 1-3)
      - Scrapbooks, 1902, 1904 (Box 15, Folder 4-6)
    - Alsop, Joseph W. (1876-1953)
      - Honors, 1953 (Box 16, Folder 7)
      - Photographs, 1898, 1938, undated (Box 16, Folder 8-11)
      - Scrapbook, undated (Box 17, Folder 12)
    - Alsop, John (1915-2000)
      - Photographs, 1962 (Box 18, Folder 13)
      - Political Cartoons, 1962 (Box 18, Folder 14)
      - Miscellaneous, 1962 (Box 18, Folder 15)
    - Alsop, Stewart [writings], 1957, 1959 (Box 18, Folder 16)
    - Alsop Family
      - Baby clothes, 1849 (Box 19, Folder 17)
      - Deeds, 1845-1889 (Box 20, Folder 18-19)
    - Newspapers, 1760s, 1790s (Box 43)
- Additional Material, 1790-1817; Accession 2011-M-074
  Materials consist of poems written by and plays collected by Richard Alsop (1761-1815) and the Alsop family, sales of the library of Richard Alsop, and correspondence of Richard Alsop and the Alsop family.
  - Poems and Plays
    - Aristodemus; or, Ambition and remorse, a tragedy in five acts, 1814 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      From the Italian of the Abbe Monti. By Richard Alsop, 1814. Original manuscript. In notebook.
    - Desultory poetry etc., by Richard Alsop, Undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Verses of various kinds, fragments, translations etc., copied off from a number of loose slips of paper. Manuscript notebook.
    - Julius of Tarentum, a tragedy in five acts from the German of M. Liesewitz, 1797 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Original manuscript bound in full leather. On front flyleaf: Richard Alsop's 1797.
    - Poetry by R. Alsop, Undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Manuscript notebook of verse and prose, chiefly translations from Italian.
    - Elegy (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Autograph manuscript of an original poem in the hand of F.M. Alsop.
    - Three Poems: Elegaic Lines to the Memory of R. Alsop; Verses To an Infant Boy with a Small Toy Watch; Lines Inscribed on the Alsop Family Tomb, Undated, 1814 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Epitaph (6 lines of verse) and The Parting Soul's Address to the Body, Undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Sales of the library of the late Richard Alsop, esq. at Blake & Cunningham's auction by order of Mr. Francis T. Oliver, 1817 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence
    - Alsop, Frances M. (daughter), 1809-1810 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Alsop, Joseph Wright, 1790-1796 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Alsop, Mary (sister), 1797-1815 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Alsop, Richard (son), 1804 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Oliver, Frances J. (son-in-law), 1812 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Oliver, Mary Caroline Alsop (daughter), 1808-1815 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Pomeroy, Benjamin, 1792 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Pomeroy, Elizabeth, 1813 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Pomeroy, Maria Wyllys, 1795-1809 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Additional Material, 1834-1865; Accession 2014-M-027
  - Letterpress book of outgoing correspondence of Joseph Wright Alsop, 1834-1865 (Box 1)